Guide to the Women in the Urban Crisis Records, 1969-1984 AIS.1985.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Library Materials, 1896-1981; 1960-1981; IX.
  These materials make up a reference library for some of the most important women's issues of the 1960s-80s. With a wide range of materials, from official government reports to major women's liberation organizations to local groups and events, this series provides a multifaceted view of the feminist movement in the 1960s-1980s.
  - Women's Bureau, U.S. Department of Labor, c. 1979; 1.
    - Childcare, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Family Support Systems, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Low Income Women, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Mature Women, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Non-traditional Jobs, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Occupational Safety and Health, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Pension/Social Security, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Teen Women, undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Wage Gap, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Women and Unions, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - U.S. Department of Labor, 1978-1981; 2.
    - "Alternative Routes to Education Credit" consumer information leaflet, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - "Alternative Work Patterns" brochure, undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - "Apprentice Now" booklet, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - "Employment Goals of World Plan of Action" report, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - "Job Service: How It Works for You" brochure, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - "Marital and Family Characteristics of the Labor Force, 1979" special report, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - "Perspectives on Working Women" report, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - "Placing Minority Women in Professional Jobs" monograph, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - "Where to Find BLS data on Children and Youths" brochure, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - "Where to find BLS statistics on Women" report, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - "Women in Apprenticeship" brochure, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - "Women in Domestic Work: Yesterday and Today" special report, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - "Women in the Labor Force: Some New Data Series" report, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - "Women Workers Then and Now: 1880-1980" poster (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - "A Working Woman's Guide to her Job Rights" booklet, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - "Young Workers and Families" special report, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 26)
  - U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1974-1980; 3.
    - "Dealing with the Angry Child," informational pamphlet, reprinted by National Institute of Mental Health, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 27)
    - "Grandma Called it Roughage" article reprinted from FDA Consumer, U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - "Homemaker Health Aide Service" training manual, with note from H. John Heinz III, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 29)
    - "Selected List of Post-secondary Education Opportunities for Minorities and Women" book, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 30)
    - "Social Security Information for Young Families" booklet, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 31)
    - "A Woman's Guide to Social Security" booklet, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 32)
  - Various Federal Government Agency Materials, 1973-1977; 4.
    - U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, "A Guide to Federal Laws and Regulations Prohibiting Sex Discrimination", 1976 (Box 16, Folder 33)
    - U.S. Department of Agriculture, "Good Foods" coloring book, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 34)
    - U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development, "A Report on Sex Discrimination in Five American Cities", 1975 (Box 16, Folder 35)
    - U.S. Department of State National Commission on the Observance of International Women's Year, "Justice for American Women" report, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 36)
    - U.S. Department of State National Commission of the Observance of International Women's Year, National Women's Conference "Proposed National Plan of Action", 1977 (Box 16, Folder 37)
  - Pennsylvania-Related Materials, 1972-1980; 5.
    - Community Services of Pennsylvania, "Poverty in Pennsylvania" report 3rd ed., 1979 (Box 16, Folder 38)
    - Greater Pittsburgh magazine, contains "Call for Action" event, March 1973 (Box 16, Folder 39)
    - The Hunger Action Coalition with the University of Pittsburgh Center for Urban Research, "The Hunger Crisis" report, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 40)
    - League of Women Voters of Pennsylvania and the Pennsylvania Bar Association, "Judicial Retention: Some Questions Answered" brochure, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 41)
    - National Conference on the Observance of International Women's Year and the Pennsylvania IWY Coordinating Committee materials, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 42)
    - Pennsylvania Coalition of Food and Nutrition, "Pennsylvania School Breakfast Campaign Handbook", 1980 (Box 16, Folder 43)
    - Pennsylvania Department of Education, "A Counseling Workshop Manual for Women Seeking Non-Traditional Work," by Priscilla Farmer, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 44)
    - Pennsylvania Department of Education, "Food with Love: a Guide for Orientation of Aides and Community Outreach in Child Nutrition Programs", 1976 (Box 16, Folder 45)
    - Pennsylvania Department of Justice, "Stretch Your Dollar" brochure (Box 16, Folder 46)
    - Project Pace Setter, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 47)
    - Urban League of Pittsburgh, "Handbook for Parents" prepared for Pittsburgh Public Schools, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 48)
    - Westinghouse Broadcasting Company, summary of report by the Women's Advisory Council on women in media, sent to council members, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 49)
  - Conferences, 1977-1980; 6.
    - National Women's Conference "American Women on the Move" booklet, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 50)
    - Women's Bureau 60th Anniversary conference "Women and Work in the 80's", 1980 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - The World Conference of the UN Decade for Women "Copenhagen '80: the Washington Conference for Women," U.S. Department of State, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Subject and Topical Files, 1960-1973; 17.
    - Boston Women's Health Book Collective, Our Bodies, Ourselves book, Simon and Schuster publisher materials, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 56)
    - Compilation books, includes newsletters, booklets, articles, 1968-1972 (Box 17, Folder 57-58)
    - East-West Journal newspaper, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 59)
    - Eastern Women's Center informational pamphlet, with doctor biographies, undated (Box 17, Folder 60)
    - "Female Politicians" folder, includes newspaper clippings and pamphlets, 1970-1972 (Box 17, Folder 61)
    - Fifth Street Women's Center materials; trial informational pamphlet, "Making of Fifth St Women's Building Film" pamphlet, c. 1970 (Box 17, Folder 62)
    - International Women's Calendar, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 63)
    - Liberation Enterprises feminist paraphernalia catalogue, undated (Box 17, Folder 64)
    - Proceedings of Meeting of The Assembly on University Goals and Governance American Academy of Arts and Sciences on the Role of Women in Higher Education, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 65)
    - "Publications and Bibliographies" folder, includes pamphlets, reading lists, flyers, 1970-1972 (Box 17, Folder 66)
    - "Reproduction" folder, includes articles, booklets on pregnancy, birth control, abortion, 1970-1972 (Box 17, Folder 67)
    - "Sexual Equality by Men," includes booklets and articles, c. 1960 (Box 17, Folder 68)
    - "The Source" women's liberation directory, undated (Box 17, Folder 69)
    - "Turbulent Times" speech by Ramsey Clark, reprinted by Sidney Hillman Foundation, c. 1970 (Box 17, Folder 70)
    - Vocations for Social Change, "People's Yellow Pages", 1973 (Box 17, Folder 71)
    - "Where Do We Go from Here: Chaos or Community" Martin Luther King, Jr. chapter reprinted by Sidney Hillman Foundation, c. 1967 (Box 17, Folder 72)
    - Women's Free Press, Know, Inc., list of newsletters, undated (Box 17, Folder 73)
    - Women's Heritage Calendar and Almanac, 1970-1971 (Box 17, Folder 74)
    - Women's History Library introductory letter and request for materials from Pittsburgh Women's Center, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 75)
    - WUNTRAC, Women United for Needless Trotskyist Rhetoric Action Coalition, informational sheet, undated (Box 17, Folder 76)
  - Labor, 1978-1980; 7.
    - Federal Emergency Management Agency, "Role of Women in the Fire Service" report, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Minority Women's Employment Program (MWEP), "Forward, Adelante" booklet, RTP, Inc., undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - National Commission on Working Women info sheets, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - National Manpower Institute, "Work and Service Experience for Youth", 1978 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - RTP, Inc. informational booklet, undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - RTP, Inc., "You Can Sit at a Desk All Day…" brochure on apprenticeships for women, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - "Women Appointed to Top Government Posts by President Carter" fact sheet, the office of Sarah Weddington, c. 1978 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - "Women and Work" article by Mildred Hamilton, copied from S. F. Examiner, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Other Women's Organizations, 1973-1980; 8.
    - American Association of University Women (AAUW), informational sheet and flyer, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), "What About Sex Discrimination" booklet and sex discrimination checklist, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - "The Question of Men, Women and 'Comparable Worth,'" article by Carol Krucoff, republished from The Washington Post by AFSCME, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Coalition of Labor Union Women (CLUW), informational brochure (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - National Congress of Neighborhood Women (NCNW), informational brochure, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Women's Center School, summer course offerings pamphlet, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Women's Educational Equity Communications Network (WEECN), "Girls and Women in Sports" and "Disabled Women and Equal Opportunity" resource pamphlets, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Feminist Magazines, 1969-1973; 9.
    - Aphra feminist literary magazine, 1969-1971 (Box 17, Folder 18-19)
    - Aurora Prism of Feminism magazine, June 1971 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Black Maria magazine, December 1971-April 1972 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - The Human Factor journal of the Graduate Sociology Student Union Colombia University, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - The Innovative Campus magazine, University of Pittsburgh, Fall 1970 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Lilith literary magazine, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - Motive magazine, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 25)
    - Moving Out magazine, 1971-1972 (Box 17, Folder 26)
    - Ms. Magazine, September 1972- January 1973 (Box 17, Folder 27)
    - Notes from the Second Year: Women's Liberation magazine, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 28)
    - The Opening magazine, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 29)
    - Red Clay Reader literary magazine, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 30)
    - Redbook magazine, Janurary 1972 (Box 17, Folder 31)
    - The Second Wave magazine, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 32)
    - Time magazine, "The American Woman," special issue, March 1972 (Box 17, Folder 33)
    - Up from Under magazine, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 34)
    - Velvet Glove magazine, First Anniversary issue, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 35)
    - Women: a Journal of Liberation magazine, 1969-1972 (Box 17, Folder 36)
    - Women Speaking magazine, July-September 1970 (Box 17, Folder 37)
    - Women of Viet Nam magazine, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 38)
  - Newsletters, 1970-1973; 10.
    - ALAS's newsletter, 1971-1972 (Box 17, Folder 39)
    - Atlanta Women's Liberation, "Just Like a Woman" newsletter, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 40)
    - Cincinnati Women's Liberation Newsletter, January 1971 (Box 17, Folder 41)
    - Coalition of Labor Union Women (CLUW), "CLUW News" newsletter, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 42)
    - Community Women's Center newsletter, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 43)
    - "Female Liberation Newsletter", 1973 (Box 17, Folder 44)
    - Illinois Women's Legislative Bulletin newsletter, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 45)
    - "The Lesbian Newsletter", 1971 (Box 17, Folder 46)
    - "The Link" newsletter, January 1972-December 1972 (Box 17, Folder 47)
    - National Women's Political Caucus (NWPC) newsletter, and letter to The Opening periodical, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 48)
    - "New Morning" newsletter, August 1971 (Box 17, Folder 49)
    - "Siren" newsletter, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 50)
    - Letter from "Siren" to Pittsburgh Women's Center, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 51)
    - South Bend-Mishawaka Women's Political Caucus newsletter, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 52)
    - "The Spokeswoman" newsletter, 1971-1973 (Box 17, Folder 53)
    - Washington Area Women's Center Bulletin newsletter, May 1972 (Box 17, Folder 54)
    - "The Women's Column" newsletter, reprinted by Women's Heritage Series, Inc., 1896-1900 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Women's Center newsletter, MA, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Women's Liberation Cadre, "Women's Liberation Special" newsletter, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - "Women's Liberation Newsletter", c. 1970 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - The Feminist Press Publications, 1972; 11.
    - Informational letter, introduces new publications, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - New book information and summaries: Constance de Markievicz, Firegirl, Life in the Iron Mills, Nothing But A Dog, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - "News and Notes" newsletter and catalogue, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - "What Can a Girl Do" poster, undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Women's Studies newsletter, Fall 1972 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Women's Liberation Center of New York, 1970-1973; 12.
    - Anti-rape Squad flyer to change rape legislation, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Anti-rape Squad New Years' Eve newsletter, undated (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - City-wide event calendar, January 1972 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, unaddressed form letter introducing WLC, undated (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Event calendars, January and February, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - "History of Women's Liberation Center of New York" booklet, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Minutes of General Assembly, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - Miss America demonstration flyer, c. 1971 (Box 18, Folder 17)
    - Newsletter pages, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 18)
    - Newsletter, Summer 1973 (Box 18, Folder 19)
    - "Rapists Must Not Go Free" flyer, c. 1971 (Box 18, Folder 20)
    - "Women's Abortion Project" flyer, copy of article on Women's Abortion conference, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 21)
    - WLC info flyer, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - Boston Women United, 1970; 13.
    - BWU info flyer, undated (Box 18, Folder 23)
    - "Demands of Women's Liberation" booklet, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 24)
    - "Summer Forums for Women" flyer and schedule, undated (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - Flyers for Feminist Causes, 1971-1973; 14.
    - Feminist Organization for Communication, Action, and Service (FOCAS) newsletter flyer, c. 1971 (Box 18, Folder 26)
    - Lesbian Food Conspiracy flyers and sign-up form, undated (Box 18, Folder 27)
    - "Majority Report" newsletter flyer, undated (Box 18, Folder 28)
    - National Organization for Women (NOW), child care petition flyer, undated (Box 18, Folder 29)
    - "Sistersilver" medallion flyers, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 30)
    - West Coast Lesbian Conference flyer, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 31)
    - Women's Bail fund flyer, undated (Box 18, Folder 32)
  - Child Care Materials, 1960-1970; 15.
    - Allegheny County, summer camp guide, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 33)
    - "Annotated List of Selected Publications of Day Care for Children" book, Marie Costello, 1962 (Box 18, Folder 34)
    - Childhood Education journal, 1969 (Box 18, Folder 35)
    - Louise Child Care Center informational brochure, undated (Box 18, Folder 36)
    - National Committee for the Day Care of Children, Inc., "Excerpts Related to Day Care of Children" packet, 1960 (Box 18, Folder 37)
    - National Education Association, The Step Beyond: Creativity book, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 38)
    - The New Republic, "The Day Care Problem: Kentucky Fried Children," copy of article by Joseph Featherstone, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 39)
    - New York Times magazine, "You've come a long way, Baby, in three centuries" article, by Rita Kramer, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 40)
    - U.S. Dept. of HEW, "Family Day Care and Group Day Care" article pamphlet, written by Judith Cauman, republished by Dept. of HEW, 1961 (Box 18, Folder 41)
    - U.S. Dept. of HEW, "What Good is Day Care" brochure, undated (Box 18, Folder 42)
    - U.S. Dept. of Labor and HEW, "Day Care of Children Under 12" report, 1960 (Box 18, Folder 43)
  - Arts, 1963-1972; 16.
    - Earth Onion Women's Theater informational brochure, undated (Box 18, Folder 44)
    - Feminist Book Club catalogue, vol. A, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 45)
    - Lollipop Power publisher newsletter, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 46)
    - "Natalie Petesch" folder, includes signed booklet, copies of Metro magazine, 1970-1971 (Box 18, Folder 47)
    - "Other Poets" folder, includes copies of female poets' works, undated (Box 18, Folder 48)
    - "Remember Our Fire" poetry anthology, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 49)
    - "Shit or get off the trot" joke sheet, undated (Box 18, Folder 50)
    - "Sylvia Plath" folder, includes typed copies of some of Plath's works, 1963-1971 (Box 18, Folder 51)
    - Theater performances for Women's Center flyer, undated (Box 18, Folder 52)
    - 'Unite,' and 'Women,' art by Sarah deJosephine, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 53)
    - Women's Interart Center flyer, undated (Box 18, Folder 54)
    - "Women Songs" folder, includes multiple copies of a few different feminist songs, c. 1970 (Box 18, Folder 55)